

Pablo Vera Saavedra

Santa Cruz, Bolivia 🏗

+591 70810209

pablo.diegovs@gmail.com



Passionate, highly-skilled, experienced Telecommunication Engineer with +8 years of experience in Service Provider solutions, technical leader, networking manager, experience in telco architectures, practice in implementation and designer of projects and solutions. Manage of multiple projects simultaneously.

Skills

- IP Service Provider networks specialist
- IP Network Manager
- Network services designer
- Technical leader on IP network projects
- High technical knowledge about UMMT Architecture, BGP, OSPF, IS-IS, Multicast, MPLS, MPLS-TE, Segment Routing TE, QoS
- Management of Cisco Devices (IOS, IOS XE, IOS XR, NX-OS), Huawei Routers and Firewalls Cisco Firepower
- Certified Network Developer

- Python scripting for network automation
- Programmability knowledge: Network APIs Platforms, NetConf, RestConf, YANG Models, gRPC, JSON, XML, YAML, Git, Network Telemetry, Ansible, Netmiko, Genius, Napalm.
- Certified Cisco Professional (CCNPx2)
- Focused on customer requirements and business relationship
- College professor

Education

MSc. Telecommunication Engineering with Project Management Specialization

School of Engineering - UAGRM / 2021

Post-Title on Network Technologies

FCCT-UAGRM / 2013

Telecommunication Engineer

Engineering / 2013

High School Graduate

Don Bosco High School

Language

- Spanish (Native)
- English (High Intermediate)

Certifications

- **CCNP Service Provider**
- **CCNP** Enterprise
- DevNet Specialist Cisco Enterprise Automation and Programmability
- Cisco Specialist Enterprise Design
- Cisco Specialist Enterprise Advanced Infrastructure Implementation
- Cisco Specialist Enterprise Core
- Cisco Specialist Service Provider Advanced Routing Implementation
- Cisco Specialist Service Provider Core
- Cisco Specialist Service Provider VPN Services Implementation
- **CCNA Service Provider**
- **CCNA** Enterprise
- IPv6 Advanced/LACNIC IANA
- Digital Transformation/Google Activate

Experience

Core IP Network Specialist

NuevaTel PCS/April 2019 - Present

- Developer of network management automation applications
- Management and administration of the national Core IP Network
- Management and load balancing of the national internet connections with other Service Providers
- Operations of Firewalls and security platforms
- Advice to sales teams on product portfolio
- Coordination and management of service technician's teams

College Professor and Cisco Instructor

U.D.I./ June 2016 - July 2021

- Instructor of CCNA Security, CCNA, CCDA
- College Professor of Telecommunications Systems
- College Professor of Network Security
- College Professor of Network Design

Post-Sales Engineer

2

Logicalis Latam/Jan 2018 - April 2019

- Design and implementation of a metropolitan net in the city of La Paz, Cochabamba and Santa Cruz. (Banco Bisa, 2018)
- Design of SDN Architecture for Data Center Network with Cisco ACI (Banco Económico)
- Implementation of CORE equipment's for a corporate network. (YPFB TR, 2018)
- Operation and maintenance of national data net. (PIL-Tigo, 2018)
- Support and maintenance of television net and corporate network. (Tigo, 2018)
- Advice and support management for corporate clients

Proyect and Design Engineer

ITC Servicios/April 2013 - Jan 2018

- Design and implementation of CGNAT and 6PE y 6VPE migration solutions for an ISP (Entel, 2017)
- Design and implementation of Route Reflectors distributed architecture for an ISP (Entel, 2017)
- Design and implementation of Unified MPLS Architecture. (Entel, 2017)
- Design and implementation of BNG y MCLAG solutions. (Entel, 2017)
- Design and implementation of IPTV solution for an ISP. (Entel, 2016)
- Design and implementation of Carrier Ethernet Agregation. (Entel, 2016)
- Network Optimization for an ISP (Entel, 2015)
- Implementation of Internet Peering's (ASR9010) (Entel, 2015)
- Implementation of Optimization TE and Qos on the Core IP-NGN (Entel, 2015)
- Migration and Implementation of Edge Devices (BRAS, CEoIP, MSE) (Entel, 2015)
- Implementation of FTTX services (Entel, 2014)
- Optimization Carrier-Ethernet (Entel, 2014)
- Implementation of Metro-Ethernet for Access Netowrk ISP (Entel, 2014)
- Implementation of IP RAN Backhaul (NuevaTel, 2014)
- Auditory and planification for voice and data networks (Nibol, 2014)
- Redundancy Datacenter solutions (Nexus 7000) (Entel Bolivia, 2013)
- Auditory of the risks in the network (Inesco, 2013)



